[Music]
foreign
episode 122.
today we discuss science technology
physics astrophysics all of that good
stuff
I hope you're all doing very well and
let me see who all is there with us I
can see a lot of people have already
joined the live stream I can see Deepak
navnur divyang kuhu Prashant Tejas
samarth
purobi
challenge accepted crazy brain Durga the
aquan
adarshing Shashank swapnil
mat nerd teaches physics komal
Guy Fawkes
darshan patil AME and lots of other
people good evening good day to all of
you I hope you're doing fantastically
well just the way I am
all right all right all right uh let us
get into the questions what do we have
for today
a whole bunch of questions let's get
into question number one
question number one is by multiple
people multiple people have asked me
this so I've taken just two questions to
represent what people have asked lots of
people have asked me about this so
abhimanyu says recently it was recorded
that the Earth's rotation was faster and
the Earth completed 24 hours
1.59 milliseconds in in that much less
time if this continues and the Earth's
rotation time gets accelerated
significantly what will be the effects
on us or on the solar system swapnil
says is it true that the Earth is
spinning faster than ever by the day and
it's making our days shorter okay okay
so recently it's come in the news that
apparently uh in 2022 uh of a few days
have been recorded that have been uh
quite uh
comparatively shorter than days that
have been recorded in the past and one
of the day's record that was recorded
was the shortest day ever and it but it
it was 1.59 milliseconds shorter than
the average uh uh time it takes for the
Earth to complete one rotation so the
Earth on average takes 24 hours to
complete one rotation we know that so
that works out to 86 400 seconds I think
and out of these 86 400 seconds there
was 1.59 milliseconds Less in the time
it took for the Earth to complete one
rotation so what does it mean well
so let's take let's take a bigger
picture approach yes uh in the past the
Earth used to rotate much faster
about one and a half million years one
one and a half billion with a B billion
years before present the rotation time
of the Earth was less than 19 hours in
the past it was likely even shorter so
if you look at the large-scale uh
picture it's apparent it's clear that
the Earth's rotation is slowing down
right so imagine you're you're somebody
who who trades on the stock market if
you look at the stock market graphs of
various shares over a 10-year period you
see a very clear Trend and you see
Trends uh for for companies that have
existed for a long time but if you look
at the Sharma share prices hour by hour
you're gonna see very very what seems to
be random fluctuations
so if you see it in the larger bigger
picture in that context the uh the uh
Trends or patterns become apparent and
what you see on short time scales is not
necessarily something that will
contribute to the long-term picture
but it is indeed true that this has
happened so what why has this happened
is it something that we should be
concerned about uh no we don't need to
be concerned about it uh what if if this
trend continues for the short for the
short foreseeable future then maybe we
will have to uh readjust the way we
measure time I mean we would have to
perhaps introduce a leap second in order
to make up for the shortfall of all the
shorter days and all that so that could
be a headache for programmers for
systems analysts systems people who
maintain systems you know and things
like that that could certainly be a
headache for them but for us life goes
on it doesn't make any difference over a
lot over the
past one point
five or two billion years the Earth's
rotation has been slowing down so what
are the the factors that contribute to
this the major factor that contributes
to the slowing down of the Earth's
rotation is the uh tidal effects caused
by the moon so the Earth has a satellite
the Moon yes uh imagine this red
pomegranate is the Earth and this yellow
lemon is the moon so the moon goes
around the earth and it it tugs on the
on the Earth right it has a
gravitational pull on the earth and this
effect this has the effect of slowly
over a very long period of time slowing
down the rotation period of the earth so
that is the large-scale thing and also
also we know that the moon uh causes
tides on the earth it deforms the
Earth's crust crust it bulges the
Earth's crust is not entirely spherical
it is oblong it's like squash it's like
a squashed Circle kind of yeah there is
a bulge along the equatorial line uh so
the Earth gets deformed by the gravity
of the moon it's a very small imp almost
imperceptible change but that's what
something that happens uh the gravity of
the Moon also affects the oceans the the
oceans slosh around the planet is more
than 70 Waters although this water
sloshes around that also affects the
rotation of the earth the atmosphere
itself is a fluid it also sloshes around
in a way that also affects the rotation
of the earth inside the earth we have a
molten interior we have magma enormous
in enormous pool of magma yeah spherical
and with a solid core at the center most
likely yes so this magma
that also is a fluid it's a very viscous
thick and very hot fluid that also
sloshes around that also has currents it
circulates it's what generates the
um Earth's magnetic field
so the Earth is an extremely complex
system
there are billions maybe trillions of
parameters that you have to take into
account in order to understand why
things happen the way they do right so
uh
so that's the situation that is what we
have that's the planet we are living in
that's what we have lived on in over the
past two billion two million years us as
the human species yes
uh so this is not a cause for concern
it's not going to suddenly uh in a few
years shorten the shorten the day this
is a very small change over a large
period of time the uh the day is going
to get longer actually
so in the future as the day gets longer
as the moon recedes from the earth solar
eclipses will end you will have partial
solar eclipses but the total solar
eclipse that we experienced today is not
going to happen in the distant future so
that's the kind of thing that's uh
that's in store for us in the very
distant future the thing about us is
that uh human life is is very brief it's
the human life is ephemeral from a
geological standpoint from that
perspective it's it's an eye blink of
time
so we think that a hundred years is a
big deal that's nothing in the in the in
the larger picture so that's why we we
are worried about milliseconds and micro
seconds which don't really make any any
big difference in the large in the
larger scheme of things right so that's
what's happening and why is has the
Earth been rotating slightly faster in
the in the past uh in in recent times we
don't quite know why it's white so like
I said there are lots and lots of
factors that go into this most likely
there is there is it's because of some
something to do with the tithes
so the way the tides have been sloshing
around on the planet somehow that seems
to have made the planet temporarily
rotate just a little bit faster 1.5 or
so milliseconds faster than average but
over a long period of time it's going to
actually get slower so this is something
that has happened this is something we
observe maybe we need to uh in our
systems in our computer systems in our
time keeping systems we need to account
for this chain maybe throw in a leap
second if required so that could be a
headache for programmers for systems for
people who maintain systems and all that
but otherwise it's not a big deal it's
not an issue this is just part of nature
that's how nature goes all right so this
is a phenomenon you see everywhere not
just on the Earth every single planet
that has atmosphere that has an internal
magma pool magma layer Etc all these
planets even moons their period of
rotation changes it varies or if they
have multiple moons the moons could
affect that if there's a single Moon
even then there's a there is this
phenomenon that happens so that is
what's going on it is not something that
is going to make much of a difference to
life on Earth
and uh yeah so that's where we are
let's take question two
mayuk says researchers at Yale
University have been successful in
restoring cellular and organ functions
in dead pigs is this a major advancement
can it revolutionize medicine in a way
although Peta has criticized it so I I
don't know what Peter has said or not
said I am not concerned with that
um let's talk about this this
interesting piece of news so yes I did
see this news recently so what happened
is that in the past I think in 2019 what
they had done is that they took pigs
They removed the brains which obviously
necessitates killing the pigs They
removed the brains and kept the brains
well outside the big body which means
that the brain is starved of oxygen
right for an hour or maybe four hours or
something and then they ran some fluid
through the brain some kind of fluid
that they've designed which is mixed
with the blood of the pigs and they were
able to in some way revive revive some
of the electrical activity in those
disembodied pig brains so there is
something that they had done in 2019 so
now this year what they have done is
that they have taken entire pigs without
removing the brains and
they took they acquired these pigs from
some livestock company they monitored
the pigs for a few days maybe three days
or so you know to see that they are
stable the vital signs are fine and all
then the pigs were sedated anesthetized
you know put to sleep but still alive
then Cardiac Arrest was induced by
administering an electrical shock to the
pig hearts which results in the pig's
death yeah so the pigs would die then
the pigs were uh left alone the dead
pigs once the heart stopped were left
alone for about an hour or so
and then this special solution that this
company these researchers have developed
that special solution was run through
the pig's bodies mixed with the pig's
blood and even after an hour had elapsed
once the pigs died and then this
solution was administered what they saw
was that there was some Revival of
activity cellular cellular activity and
uh activity I think in the big hearts in
in the kidneys I believe and possibly
liver also
some sort of activity resumed cellular
activity so what happens when an
organism dies is that as soon as an
organism dies which is typically taken
as when the heart stops functioning
so when there is cardiac arrest the
final Cardiac Arrest the heart stops
functioning
what happens is that the blood stops
flowing in that organism in that
animal's body when the blood stops
flowing the cellular tissues all the
organs are immediately starved of oxygen
we breathe in that process is what
oxygenates the blood the oxygen
is mixed into the blood via the lungs
and it is pumped through the body by the
heart that's what happens so once an
organism dies once an animal dies the
organs and the tissues and the cells are
very rapidly in a matter of minutes
starved of oxygen this is essentially
cellular death and as soon as the normal
functioning of the organs and the cells
ends it is it is terminated what happens
is that there are enzymes within the
cells that start digesting the cellular
walls of the cells which essentially
is the process of decomposition so
decomposition starts very rapidly within
minutes of an organism dying that is
what we know that is what we know
through biology through research
and yet even after an hour had elapsed
after the after the pigs stood their
hearts stop beating they were able to
revive some sort of cellular function in
the cells in the tissues of the pigs and
even in organs like the heart I believe
and even the kidneys possibly the liver
I don't remember exactly what it was so
that's what they were able to achieve uh
they did not detect any electrical
activity in the brains which could
possibly be because of two reasons first
of all the solution they had uh in they
had injected into the pig's bodies which
revived the pigs to some extent that
solution was at a colder at a lower
temperature than what the pig's blood
would be so maybe that lower temperature
ensured that the uh or the brain did not
show any electrical activity
and maybe there was some anesthetic also
in that solution which could have
suppressed uh any activity that would
otherwise have happened in the brains of
those pigs so maybe in the future they
could tweak the parameters keep the
maybe uh remove the anesthetic component
from the fluid and maybe Elevate the
fluid to the average normal Pig blood
temperature and maybe that could
possibly even demonstrate some activity
electrical activity in the brains right
so in this experiment they were able to
see heightened cellular activity in
organic activity which kind of and and
when certain
um
and they also observed involuntary
twitching of the pig's necks and various
other muscles uh when this happened when
they injected the solution
so this does
uh this is indeed a kind you could you
could consider this to be a landmark
experiment that even one hour after
cellular after cardiac arrest the pigs
were revived to some extent uh the
brains were not aware but maybe in the
future they would be they may be able to
uh revive some activity in the brains
also so this brings into question that
this raises questions about what is the
exact definition of death
uh there are multiple definitions from
the medical perspective of death the
standard definition is cardiac arrest
when the heart stops beating that is
when uh the animal or the or or a person
is that is recorded as a time of depth
when the heart finally stops beating but
uh we know that in certain cases people
who go into Commerce their heart stops
beating they can be revived after 10
minutes even after 20 minutes that that
has happened multiple times especially
when a person let's say drowns in in
very cold water even 20 minutes after
drowning because the water is so cold it
it stops decomposition it keeps the
organs in in the brain Etc reasonably
intact and even after 20 minutes or so
it's happened multiple times that the
person could be revived and the person
went back to life as if and then they
were able to resume normal life
afterwards uh so Cardiac Arrest is one
definition of death that is typically
recorded as a time of death the other
definition is that the the uh
the secession of of brain activity all
electrical activity in the brain so a
person could be alive the body could be
functioning the heart may be beating but
there is zero brain activity so that is
brain death right a person whose brain
did or in a vegetative state so there
are multiple definitions of what death
actually is yeah so when a person is
brain dead you are allowed to donate
their organs their family members
immediate family are allowed to go and
donate the orchids because the person's
brain no longer exists there's no
consciousness it's just a vegetative
vegetative state
now this experiment raises questions
about what exactly death is even after
one hour of cardiac arrest they were
able to revive some function in the
organs in the future they may who knows
in the future they may be able to revive
much more of organ function possibly
even brain function
which would then raise significant
ethical issues ETC about what brain
about what death actually is I mean is
it that we are
uh we are the
we are certifying somebody dead
prematurely is that the norm that we've
been following yeah so so it's still
something that needs to be researched
it's still something some a lot of
research needs to be done about this
um but yes it raises interesting
questions it raises somewhat troubling
questions about what the what death
actually is
uh so yes more research needs to be done
in this will be the research will be
done because it's the it's the what what
people call the Holy Grail right coming
back from the from death
so if that sort of thing can could be
done it could revolutionize medicine and
people would possibly never ever die if
you take it to the ultimate conclusion
so that's what's happening that's where
we are that is the experiment uh and uh
it's still a work in progress It's not a
final result it's just maybe one of the
initial steps in a long journey yeah so
that is what this experiment is about
and uh they are going to continue the
research in and and take it forward
so this now says what's the difference
between a cheetah and a leopard because
although cheetah has been extinct from
India a lot of people tend to confuse
between the two a moreover which one of
the two is more dangerous than the other
do you think that while doing science
everything mentioned in fact must be
taken literally with the little meaning
only
uh let me take the cheetah versus
leopard question I'm not sure what the
other question is right so what's the
difference between the cheetah and a
leopard well uh leopards I think are
much more powerful and if you look at
the face of a cheetah and leopard they
are both cats yes of course the cheetahs
have this uh signature marking on the
face that it's like tears Black Tears uh
let me just put that on the screen so
that you you can see the difference
between a cheetah and a leopard
all right let's uh Google cheetah
so what does a cheetah look like so
let's see that she does face cheetah
face so there you have the face of a
cheetah as you can see there are these
the signature markings on the face that
look like uh flowing tears but it's
black these are black markings here's
another one so all cheetahs have this
black marking and as you can see
cheetahs have these slender and long
bodies they are the fastest animals on
the planet
uh they are quite delicate actually
cheetahs and cheetah
versus human let's see the scale
people and humans so as you can see uh
this is the size comparison between a
cheetah and a human being this is uh
yeah that's what it looks like so it's a
it's a medium-sized cat it's much larger
than our standard house cats or domestic
cats it's much larger but compared to
other calves of cheetahs have slender
bodies and are somewhat delicate what
does a leopard look like
and and cheetahs cannot Roar you don't
have they are not able to produce a
roaring sound cheetahs sound like house
cats the meow meow meow that's what they
do leopards
can roar and and they are much more
strongly built they don't have those
markings on their face they've got spots
leopards have spots uh yeah this is a
comparison between the cheetah and a
leopard
and leopards are much more dangerous in
my opinion than cheetahs cheetahs also
are obviously they are wild cats they
are large cats they are dangerous but
leopards are way more powerful
physically stronger than cheetahs and
the stockier that the build is different
as you can see
so leopard versus human let's say this
size difference
foreign
okay these are very unfortunate images
but uh leopard humans okay so this is
the size difference this looks like a
snow leopard which is one of the
varieties of leopard that we have in
India in Northern India
um so leopards look like they are
somewhat smaller than cheetahs but they
are way more powerful than cheetahs okay
let me not show such images here that's
a kind of
all right let's go back to the leopard
so that's the difference leopards can
roar cheetahs cannot Roar leopards the
face doesn't have those tear tier
markings cheetahs they do have it right
and leopards are somewhat smaller but
they are way more powerful than cheetahs
way more physically stronger than
cheetahs and of course the Indian
cheetah is extinct but we are
reintroducing The Cheetah into India uh
we are acquiring kitas from South Africa
as well as Namibia
uh so that is what is the most recent
developments so I believe that cheetahs
are slightly shorter and stockier than
sorry I believe leopards are slightly
smaller in size than cheetahs cheetahs
have a longer body
but cheetahs are more delicately built
they are built for Speed not for
strength and power leopards
are stronger they can they can take a
deer
by its neck clamp it in their jaws and
lift that deer which may actually be
larger than the leopard they can lift it
all the way up to a tree that's kind of
incredible immense physical strength
that the leopards have cheetahs are not
that not quite that strong leopards are
very hard to domesticate and tame but
you can domesticate any of these large
cats but you could kind of tame some of
them cheetahs are almost like house cats
if you raise a cheetah from the time
it's a kitten it's gonna be just like a
house cat it's not gonna be that
dangerous leopards are a whole different
story you will not see any YouTube
videos of people having a leopard as a
pet but you may see humans having two
thousand pets as pets or caracals or
other Wildcats cats
so uh that is the overall difference
between cheetahs and leopards cheetahs
used to be abundantly available in India
your cheetahs everywhere they were
almost like like like cats here uh the
turkic emperor
uh what was his name jahangir I think he
I believe he had five thousand pet
cheetahs in a menagerie or whatever so
that's how abundant cheetahs were in
India and a couple of about three four
centuries ago uh they were decimated by
the British
and that's what happened now we are
reintroducing them leopards we still
have them in India leopards uh yeah
so which one is more dangerous
definitely the leopard the leopard is
much more dangerous
and yeah so that is the answer to this
question
okay this the question is
why do different sizes of black holes
exist and what do you mean by different
sizes of infinity
yes yes yes uh okay let's first talk
about black holes well stars come in
different sizes planets come in
different sizes galaxies come in
different sizes similarly black holes
come in different sizes uh black hole
may be born from Stellar collapse from a
star that is like let's say 20 20 times
the mass of the sun
yeah
but if it is in a dense neighborhood
where there are lots of clouds of gas
and other stuff it may then swallow all
that gas and grow larger over time
larger larger larger yeah if you have a
black hole that's the center of a
supermassive black if you have a black
hole that's at the center of a galaxy
most Galaxies have super massive black
holes at the center in some cases this
guy these black holes are active black
holes that are actively swallowing more
mass clouds of gas and dust and stuff
those black holes will grow over time so
that's why do you have black holes of
different sizes different masses some
stars that collapse into black holes do
so at the at the end of a supernova
explosion some Stars simply collapse
overnight into black holes one day it's
there the next day it's all dark what
happened where did the star go it winked
out and became a black hole so there are
different processes and through which
black holes are formed black holes could
even have formed in the very early
Universe the primordial Universe those
are the hypothetical primordial black
holes which may be very small we we have
never observed any but the it's
certainly Allowed by physics yes maybe
there could have been lots of time
primordial incredible amounts of
primordial black holes that were formed
maybe they could form some part of dark
matter or or bound states of primordial
black holes may may be a component of
the cold dark matter that we know exists
in the universe and so on
so that's why black holes come in
different sizes all right different
masses uh and so on now what about the
different sizes of infinity now this is
an interesting question and I
and to explain this I should show
something on the screen uh I am sure you
all know what a number line is yes
let me put a number line on the screen
with which I shall demonstrate that
Infinity comes in different sizes
so here we have a number line we have
three number lines let's take a look at
the top most number line uh which goes
in both directions it's from 0 1 2 3 4
all the way to ten and the arrows
indicate that the number line goes on up
to Infinity in both directions so 10 11
12 Etc and from 0 if you go to the left
it is 0 minus 1 minus 2 all the way to
minus infinity right that is number line
number one
now let us take so essentially between
0 and 10 how many numbers do you have
one two three four five six seven eight
nine four numbers
now let's take the space between 0 and
1. you can construct a number line
between 0 and 1 as well and you have the
decimals right the 0.10.20.3 all the way
to 0.9 and then 1.0 now let's take the
space between 0 and 0.1 between that you
have a whole different number line 0.01
0.02 and so on all the way to 0.09 and
0.10
and you can go deeper and deeper into it
between 0 and 0.01 you will have
other numbers and so on what I'm trying
to say is that between 0 and 10 you can
place an infinite number of numbers
so there is an Infinity there is an
infinite number of points or numbers
between 0
and 10.
that is infinity
you also have an infinite number of
points or numbers between 0 and 1. that
is also Infinity
you also have an infinite number of
points or numbers between 0 and 0.1 that
is also Infinity
so we are talking about three different
Infinities here between 0 and 10 between
0 and 1 and between 0 and 0.1 all three
are Infinity but we know that the space
between 0 and 10 is larger than the
space between 0 and 1.
and that space is larger than the space
between 0 and 0.1
what does this tell us it tells us that
Infinities come in different sizes
which doesn't make sense but when you
look at the number line it becomes clear
that even though all these three
quantities are Infinities they have
different sizes which means that certain
infinities
are larger than other infinities and as
a kid when you first understand this
concept it kind of causes a little bit
of brain damage
so yeah that's what we mean by different
sizes of infinity infinity is infinite
and yet it comes in different sizes that
is the strangest thing you come across
as a kid I mean if you ever think of it
in mathematics yeah so that's what we
mean by different sizes of infinity
okay swapnil says can you explain the
Drake equation hypothesized by the
astrobiologist Frank Drake
was it a legitimate or a failed
experiment the break equation is not an
experiment it's an equation
uh it is an equation that seeks to uh
kind of put a number on put put
give us a handle or give us an
approximate idea of how many intelligent
civilizations exist within our own home
Galaxy
non-earth not non-human civilizations so
let me show you what this equation is
like it's got a number of parameters
let us share the screen
here it is
yes so this is the drag equation okay n
is the number of detectable civil
civilizations in the Milky Way galaxy in
our home Galaxy n is equal to R star
times FP times n e times f i times times
FL times fi times FC times L now what do
this parameters mean
n is what we want to see what we want to
calculate the number of detectable
civilizations currently that currently
exist in the Milky Way galaxy in our
home Galaxy our star is the rate at
which stars are born
per year how many stars are born in the
Milky Way per year let's say it's one
let's say it's ten whatever the number
is so we will have to so that is the the
meaning of r star what is FP it is the
fraction of though of stars that hosts
planets so let's say you have
take any random 100 stars in the Milky
Way at random how many of these stars
have planets
so that is the faction that we are
talking about right the fraction of
stars that host planets n e is the
number of habitable planets per
planetary system
yes so out of these stars that actually
have planets how many of these
uh planetary systems or Star systems
have planets that are actually habitable
like Earth what it means is how many of
these uh have Earth-like planets that
faction f l is the fraction of those
planets on which life actually evolves
and that is something we have to
completely guess because we have never
found life anywhere except for Earth but
we may be able to guess
arrive at an intelligent guess as to
what is the fraction of those planets on
which life evolves if I is the fraction
of life that evolves intelligence FC is
the fraction of intelligent life that
becomes communicative that develops
communicative Technologies
and L is the average length of time that
civilizations are detectable
so if you multiply multiply all these
parameters together it gives you n which
is the number of detectable
civilizations that currently exist in
the Milky Way galaxy now a lot of a lot
of these parameters are simply guesswork
we can uh give we could uh
calculate R star reasonably accurately
maybe it's around one star per year or
ten Stars per year somewhere somewhere
around that
FP also because we have now a lot of
observational data it looks like the
fraction of stars that host parents
could be close to one 0.5 or 1 based on
how many we have observed we know there
are lots of exoplanets out there it
looks like planets are very common so it
could be close to one the FP n e
uh could be around 0.1 or so maybe 0.2
I'm just guessing here yeah if if L we
don't know
we don't know let's say
it is it's it's one or let's say it's
0.5 whatever that's another guess if I
is absolutely conjectural we have no
idea of knowing but we could put in a
number just to see how it works FC also
we don't know and L
is again guesswork so as you can see
this is an equation that that involves a
lot of guesswork you plug in different
values for these parameters you get very
different wildly different values of n n
is the number of detectable
civilizations that currently exist right
now as of today in the Milky Way galaxy
right so this is not an experiment this
is this is a an equation that serves as
the beginning of a conversation
yeah so I think it was developed as part
of the seti project cities search for
extraterrestrial intelligence so when
this uh project started which sought to
detect signs of uh intelligent life in
other parts of the of the Galaxy and
other galaxies possibly uh
people the the scientists wanted to
under to have some kind of a number as
to how many as to how common or uncommon
or rare
intelligent life could be in our galaxy
and that is what gave rise to this
equation and as you can see we don't
have hard numbers that we could plug
into this so a lot of it is guesswork
and based on this guesswork the number
of air the N the value of n ranges from
1 to thousands possibly
so that's how it is but it's an
interesting conversation starter and
it's something that uh
that people discuss from time to time so
that is what this Drake equation is
it's not an experiment it's an equation
which seeks
to kind of give us a handle on how many
intelligent civilizations could
currently exist in our home Galaxy
romit says what is your take on the
Fermi Paradox okay what is the Fermi
paradox
the Fermi Paradox could be asked in the
form of a question where are all the
aliens
right there are so many stars in our
galaxy how many hundred hundred billion
I believe it's a hundred billion plus
give or take
those many stars in our home galaxy The
Milky Way 100 billion let's say
how many galaxies exist out there I
believe uh hundreds of billions maybe
200 billion galaxies
in the known universe possibly yeah
so if you calculate and let's say all
Galaxies have approximately the same
number of stars the Milky Way and so on
so if you calculate the number of stars
in the observable universe it's about 10
days of 23 or 24. one with 23 or 24
zeros after that after it give or take
right
that is an incredibly large number of
stars and I mean it's it's hard to
conceive such a large number so if you
have so many stars in The observed
universe
is it not likely that that will be there
will be life out there that life could
be quite common there could be billions
trillions of intelligent civilizations
out there right it should be quite
common given the enormous number of
stars that exist in the observable
universe
so if life is should be that common
statistically speaking if life should be
that common then where are all the
aliens where are they why don't we see
any of them that is the Fermi Paradox
that is the question that I believe
Enrico Fermi asked to his colleagues
that's it for me paradox statistically
speaking life should be common so if it
is common why don't we see any signs of
Life anywhere that is it and there are
lots of different possible answers to
that uh one answer is that life is not
common we are the only life out there in
the entire universe which makes us
incredibly unique that is one possible
solution to the Fermi Paradox the other
solution is that life is everywhere but
it doesn't want us to see it
there is something called the zoo
hypothesis the Earth is a zoo
and we are being observed but we have no
idea we are being observed think of it
like this
think of a petri dish in which you have
microbes a colony of microbes a few
million microbes
or let's say let's say 8 billion
microbes
living in a petri dish
that's petri dish is in a lab
and scientists are observing it through
a microscope
and in this petri dish these bacteria
they're talking to each other we are so
intelligent but we see no life out there
where is all the life
yeah and they have no idea that they are
currently being observed so maybe
there could be intelligences out there
that are so highly Advanced that
compared to them we are like little
bacteria yes
and we have no means of knowing that we
are currently actively being observed
and studied so that is a possibility the
zoo hypothesis the other there are
various other possibilities there is the
great filters hypothesis that life could
actually be common but there are certain
hard barriers that life encounters that
ensures that we don't get to see that it
exists
maybe a life intelligent life has a
tendency to destroy itself we have
developed various technologies that are
very dangerous nuclear weapons Etc maybe
in the future we may run into a great
barrier a nuclear war which and
highlights everything that is a
possibility or or sends us back to the
Stone Age that's a possibility right or
there could be certain cataclysmic
events you know that kill off life every
once in every few million or billion
years that is also a possibility
Extinction events Global catastrophes
cataclysmic events like uh
uh there are lots of astrophysical
events that could end life right
on a planet so that sort of thing is
there uh
maybe maybe it may be the case that once
a civilization becomes reaches a certain
Stage IT transmits information
for a certain time period and then the
Transmissions stop
so we still have radio waves which go
out into into space
but eventually our technologies will
become so effective that efficient that
we will not have to broadcast
the radio waves into the atmosphere and
into space we may be able to communicate
without doing that so we may stop
transmitting right so maybe in a century
or so we may no longer be transmitting
The Way We Were transmitting in the 20th
century and even right now so maybe
intelligent civilizations transmit only
for a century or two and then all
transmissions stop that is a possibility
there may be a possibility that
intelligent life is common but it is
very dangerous to other intelligent life
and that's why all intelligent
civilizations try to hide themselves I
think it's called The Dark Forest
hypothesis let's say you are traveling
in the night through a forest it's a
dark Forest right
now
we know that in this Dark Forest there
are other animals some could be nice but
there could be Tigers there could be
leopards there could be pythons there
could be crocodiles and various other
things
so what is the optimum way of
being in a dark Forest try to stay
hidden
you may encounter an animal that is
harmless but you may encounter an animal
that may terminate you
so the optimum solution is to assume
that all life that exists in this Dark
Forest is out to kill me be
extraordinarily paranoid and hide
yourself
that is the best
um Optimum solution for survival
so that is a dark Forest hypothesis that
all life assumes all intelligent life
assumes that any other intelligent
intelligence it encounters
is uh life-threatening for it and that's
why you hide yourself you don't transmit
you just stay hidden so there could be
lots of other civilizations out there
but they are not stupid enough to
broadcast their location
and that kind of tells us that we should
not be stupid enough to send radio waves
into space and broadcast our location to
various stars like some astronomers and
and scientists have done that may be a
very very very
um
bad thing to do and so on so there are
different uh such
theories hypotheses that have been put
forth we don't quite have the solution
right now because thus far we have not
found any sign of even non-intelligent
life beyond our home planet there could
be there are potential locations in our
own solar system where microbial life or
or lower level life could exist
uh places like Venus Venus is a
possibility Mars is a possibility
um the the Moon Europa the moon Titan
Etc there could be other places
in our own solar system where life could
exist there could be a subsurface ocean
on Pluto itself where possibly life may
exist if it is liquid water
then it is warm reasonably warm and wife
could exist there so there are lots of
possibilities
so if we are able to find life somewhere
else in our own solar system first of
all that could indicate that life could
be really very common out there and
that's why and and then if life indeed
exists elsewhere it means that a certain
percentage certain fraction of the life
becomes intelligent like in the Drake
equation there is a fraction there is a
there is a term for that let me put that
back on the screen
here is the drinking into the brake
equation the fraction of life that
evolves intelligence f i
so there would be once we know that life
does Exist Elsewhere
then it This this term if I comes into
the picture and so on
so there are different hypotheses we
don't quite know what what's going on we
are still like those little microbes in
a Petri dish yeah we may think that we
are hyperintly intelligent and all that
we have all this technology at our
disposal all this science at our
disposal and yet we may be like those
microbes compared to other
hypothetical
intelligent beings yeah so that is what
the Fermi Paradox is
Abhishek says what orbit does the James
Webb Space Telescope follow does it
orbit the Earth or the Sun
the James Webb Space Telescope is
orbiting the L2 LaGrange a point now
what is a LaGrange Point what is this
thing
so
we have the Earth Sun System let me
bring in my fruits again
so imagine that this pomegranate red is
the Sun
imagine that this little yellow lemon is
the Earth
so we have the Earth Sun System the sun
is large the Earth is way smaller than
the sun all right
both have a gravitational attraction and
the earth goes around the Sun in an
orbit right
so if we look at the gravitational pull
of the sun which is much larger than the
the Earth and let's say you have a third
object that you want to place between
the Earth and the Sun there will be
and if you draw a straight line between
the Earth and the Sun there will be a
place on the straight line where the
gravitational pull of the Earth and the
Sun cancels each other out and that
object may be able to remain
indefinitely in that place
that is the L1 LaGrange Point let me
show you a an image a schematic of this
what do these LaGrange points look like
there are five of them
here we are so the L1 LaGrange point is
the point between its an equilibrium
point between the Earth and the Sun it
is not quite stable
it is what's called called A metastable
LaGrange point there is another Point
called L2 which is in the same straight
line but it's behind the Earth
so in the straight in the straight line
between the Earth and the sun behind the
Earth there is another equilibrium point
called the L2 LaGrange point and that's
where the James Webb Space Telescope has
been parked
other telescopes were also have also
been parked there like the W map
telescope
Wilkinson microscope micro wave a
nisotropy probe W map I believe it's
called
then there is an L3 point that is behind
the on the other side
so if you take a straight line between
the Earth and the Sun then on the other
side you have the L3 point and then you
have the two equilateral triangle points
L4 and L5 so if you take the Sun the
earth and the L4 that forms an
equilateral triangle and similarly for
L5 also we have an equilateral tying
triangle The L4 and L5 LaGrange points
are reasonably stable they are not meta
stable they're actually stable you put
something there it will stay there
but if you put something in L1 or L2 or
L3 those points are kind of meta stable
so you need to spend a little bit of
energy a little bit of fuel to keep that
spacecraft in that point in the future
you may have spacecraft even space
stations stationed at these points maybe
in 100 years maybe not two maybe in 200
years if we if we do well if we evolve
our technology further we may have
spacecraft space stations sitting at L3
uh L5 especially at L for an L5 right
so these are LaGrange points and that's
where and especially at L2 that's where
we park spacecraft it's not very stable
so the spacecraft needs to have some
fuel small rocket engines to
periodically adjust the orbit
so that it stays in place so the James
Webb's Space Telescope is not exactly at
L2 it is orbiting the L2 LaGrange point
so the these points are called LaGrange
points because they were first
calculated by a guy called LaGrange
about two or three hundred years before
today look it up if you if you're
interested when exactly that happened
right there was a mathematician
uh so that's what it is right that's
what that's where the James Webb Space
Telescope is parked in orbit around the
L2 LaGrange point it's interesting that
it's not only the Earth that has
LaGrange points even the Earth Moon
system is LaGrange points but that is
kind of messed up by the enormous
gravitational pull of the Sun
Jupiter has LaGrange points the uh
Jupiter's LaGrange points are called the
Trojan points
uh so if you look at uh
imagine instead of the earth we have
Jupiter the Jupiter will also have all
the same LaGrange points but for in the
case of Jupiter they are called the
Trojan points and in in The L4 and L5
regions of Jupiter we have these I don't
know thousands or millions of asteroids
that Clump around that place they are
called the Trojan asteroids right so
Jupiter is Like a Shepherd and the Sheep
are all these millions of Trojan
asteroids that Clump in the lagrangian
points of Jupiter so that's a natural
phenomenon that we observe so that is
what the LaGrange points are and that is
where jwst is parked in orbit around the
L2 LaGrange point
rushal says what is orbital eccentricity
all right what is first of all forget
about orbital eccentricity what is
eccentricity from the point of view of
geometry
so
in geometry
or you we all know what a circle looks
like it's a circle
we also have something called an ellipse
in Geometry it's a conic section uh let
me put that on the screen conic sections
so that you actually get to see it
chronic sections and let me put that on
the screen
give me a second
ervr coding sections no map today only
conic sections all right these are konic
sections so if you take a cone and you
slice it up that's what we get we get
circles we get ellipses we get parabolas
we get hyperbolas in each of these guys
has its own equation and you can study
it if you're interested right cornic
sections so a circle is perfectly
circular
an ellipse is like a squashed Circle you
dig a circle and you squash it you get
an ellipse so an ellipse has something
called eccentricity
let's take a look at
the eccentricity of ellipse
all right so every ellipse has a certain
eccentricity which you can which is part
of the formula which is C by a and so on
now let me show you the eccentricity of
orbits
orbital eccentricity right or we tell
eccentricity
so orbits are like ellipses and here is
an example of orbital
eccentricity let me put that on a
different page
and show you that page so that you get a
better idea of what it is
so the inlet so the orbits of the
various planets Etc around the Sun are
not perfectly circular they are
elliptical orbits
and that's what it looks like so
based on the different uh
values of the eccentricity we get these
different shapes of ellipses and the
same goes for satellites you could have
satellites in a circular orbit you could
have satellites in squash elongated or
elliptical orbits and each orbit has a
certain value of its eccentricity and
that's what orbital eccentricity is
all right so it's all about the geometry
you study geometry you will immediately
understand what uh
what eccentricity is now let me show you
the various orbits
let me quickly show you what elliptical
orbits look like in the solar system
so in the solar system none of the
orbits of the planet planets is
perfectly spherical let's take a look at
this
so there is a hypothetical planet nine
and various other objects in the solar
system they all have orbits with varying
eccentricity
right so that's what we mean by orbital
all right hope that makes sense
right moving on to the next question
Brown nerd says
since only about five percent of the
oceans have been explored do you believe
there's intelligent life deep in the
oceans beings such as mermaids and
Mormon and more beings right
um
I believe it's indeed true that we have
explored next to nothing of the oceans
the oceans are are com are almost
completely unknown to us right uh light
goes penetrates the ocean about two
depth to a depths of about 100 meters so
if you go below 100 meters into the
ocean it's all dark there's no light at
all you have bioluminescent fish and
organisms Etc but that is few and far
between
so the vast amount of the ocean out
there is dark there's no light and we
don't quite know what what lurks deep
beneath the surface of the oceans
we have submarine cables and all which
we've been able to lay we have sonars
that tell us what the surface of the
Ocean looks like yeah we have submarines
that make use of the these undersea uh
features that navigate through them we
have detailed maps topological maps of
the subsurface Sub sub ocean surface of
the Earth and so on so we have some idea
but we haven't actually been there and
seen what exactly what kind of life is
there so it is possible that there could
be lots of unknown species that lurk in
the Deep depths of the oceans yes indeed
true people speculate there could be
certain varieties of dinosaurs that may
exist they may have evolved the ability
to to you know
to do that without oxygen to to have
gills or whatever possibly and and live
and and
respirate the way ship of fishes do Etc
so it is very likely that there could be
a large number of completely unknown
species of of fish and other marine life
that we still haven't encountered or
discovered thus far that is certainly
possible that is there is a fact it's
there we discovered new species every
year you know marine species that that
happens all the time
when it comes to intelligent life I
believe it's unlikely the probability is
low it's not zero the probability is not
zero but I think the probability is low
why do I say that because intelligent
life one of the signs one of the
Hallmarks of intelligence is curiosity
if you are intelligent you're going to
be curious about what else is out there
and you may travel you may Venture
around the oceans and if you travel if
you venture if you go to new places you
will be discovered
so intelligent life has this tendency to
to be discovered to make itself known
yeah
but on the other hand if it is really
intelligent
to know that it's a wise thing to stay
away from humans
because humans humans are aggressive and
they're violent and they're destructive
and maybe they are observing us and they
know that they should stay away from us
that is also a possibility so what do I
think I believe that the probability of
intelligent life existing deep under the
oceans is low
it's not zero if it does exist then it's
very smart that it knows to stay away
from humans yeah but there is no
evidence of that
and yet it may it may possibly exist the
probability is low and remote
Karthik says animals also have blood
groups when one animal hunts another
animal doesn't the prey's blood get
infused in its body won't that cause any
harm to the Predator due to the entry of
foreign blood
um foreign blood so it's like this in
human beings we have blood groups right
and
um
if
by mistake or by accident someone were
to infuse
a person with blood who has let's say
hypothetically blood group a and you
want to infuse blood group b or
something else into the person there
would be a very strong and adverse
biological reaction which may cause the
death of that person the death of the
recipient
so we have to make sure that we match
the blood groups and we don't mix it up
right
and when it comes to the blood of other
species if you infuse that into your
body there's gonna be terrible
immunological reaction you may end up
losing your life or you may end up
getting really really sick you may have
the entry of uh
bacteria and other organisms from
another species into you and your immune
system may not know how to deal with
that and that could cause all kinds of
complications maybe even death so yes
that is there
now when an animal predates hunts
another animal let's say you have a
Tyrannosaurus Rex
okay let's not go that far back let's
say you have a lion
that uh hunts a crocodile in the river
right
so there's a big struggle in the
crocodile bites the lion the lion bites
the crocodile at the end the lion is
larger and stronger he wins he pulls the
crocodile out of the out of the river
snaps its neck and then proceeds to have
a nice big Feast right
and of course when the lion eats the
Flesh of the crocodile the blood of the
crocodile will go into the lion's
stomach now here's the difference we're
not doing a transfusion of the
crocodile's blood into the into the
lion's blood we're not doing that
the blood and the tissue Etc which is
masticated chewed Etc
goes into the elementary Canal of the
lion settles down into the stomach it is
processed over there
there are stomach acids that break down
in enzymes Etc that break down the
tissues into more into simpler uh into a
simpler form it's then transferred into
the esophagus and into the small
intestine where it is processed further
and further and further and that's what
happens
so the blood of the animal that is
preyed upon is not infused or transfused
directly into the bloodstream of the
Lion
it is it goes through the elementary
Canal into the digestive system and the
digestive system is equipped to handle
these foreign substances there is a
purifying mechanism the liver the liver
is the great purifier anything that is
harmful or toxic in any way is removed
and it is it is filtered essentially by
the liver that's why the so we have all
these Fail-Safe mechanisms in the human
human body and all animals have labors
even sharks have livers Etc right
so so that's why
it doesn't cause any harm
if you were to take
the blood of a crocodile and sedate a
lion and then Infuse that intravenously
into into the into a lion's bloodstream
that could end up killing the lion that
could cause significant amount of harm
to the lion or species X to species why
it will cause harm right but as long as
that species that animal is eating
another animal it goes through the
proper channels like they say
yeah if the blood and the tissue and the
meat Etc flesh goes through the proper
channels which is through the digestive
through the digestive system then all is
well because the digestive system has
all these checks and balances that
ensure that nothing that's not supposed
to go into the bloodstream is allowed to
go in there and that's how it works and
that's why no such harm in shoes
okay Priyanka says as we know only five
percent of the universe
that is 200 billion galaxies
are in the five percent Universe um
yes
that is indeed correct uh I don't know
how many galaxies are there in the in
the universe you can Google it let's say
it's 200 billion maybe yeah I don't
remember all the all the numbers so
let's say there are let's say there are
200 billion galaxies in the observable
universe which is a spherical ball with
U at the center right
so yes everything we observe in the
universe
is actually five percent of the mass
energy composition of the universe all
these galaxies all the stars that we
observe all the dust clouds in the
nebulae that we observe every single
thing that we observe in the universe it
actually makes up less than five percent
of the actual mass energy composition of
the universe 95 of the universe is dark
and unknown to us
we are made up of special stuff
we are electromagnetic beings that's
what we are light is an electromagnetic
phenomenon we see things the reason why
I'm not falling through the chair that
I'm sitting in is because of the
electromagnetic force and the public
solution principle and so on so forth
right that's why matter has occupies
occupies space and so on so yes what you
are saying is correct everything that we
observe is the entire universe is just
five percent of the mass energy
composition of the universe
foreign
says what is dark matter and dark energy
well good follow-up question what is
dark matter and what is dark energy
so obviously this is something I've
answered lots of times but for the sake
of for the benefit of those who have
joined recently for the new viewers let
me explain what is dark matter and dark
energy so uh everything we observe like
I said in the universe every single
Galaxy every single star every single
exoplanet every single gas cloud every
single nebula everything we observe
makes up only five percent about five
percent of somewhat less than five
percent of the actual mass energy
composition of the universe that we live
in of The observed Universe about
68 percent of the mass energy
composition of the universe is what we
call Dark Energy in about 27 percent is
what we call dark matter if you want to
keep it simple make it 70 25 70 Dark
Energy 24 25 Dark Matter five percent
visible matter of which we are made
so how do we know this
oh we were able to figure out that
something called Dark Matter exists
because Galactic because of Galactic
rotation curves let me show you what
those are
Galactic rotation curves what are these
things let's let's put that on the
screen yes
so this is an example this is a very
famous graph Galactic rotation curves
so when you see a Galaxy galaxies rotate
we know that we know that galaxies
rotate around the center of mass
so uh
when you see the amount of mass visible
Mass a galaxy has based on its
luminosity and various other things we
expect it to to rotate at a certain
speed
And yet when we actually do the
observations of galaxies all across the
universe the observable universe we find
that the rotation speed is different
it's as if there is much more mass in
the Galaxy than what we are seeing
right so it is because of this
phenomenon this observational evidence
which which we were able to see over and
over again in all kinds of galaxies it's
because of this that we were able to
figure out that there is some unseen
matter that lurks around galaxies so all
Galaxies have a dark matter hello
which also rotates with the Galaxy right
and that's why we have this difference
in what we between what we expect and
what we actually observe so let me see
Galactic Hollow what it looks like
what does the galactic Halo look like so
typically a hollow is more or less
spherical
yeah
and uh all most galaxies are enveloped
or shrouded in these dark matter Hallows
so this is one example a galaxy galaxy
has is a flat kind of thing a spiral
galaxy is more or less flat it has a
galactic plane and yet there is a dark
matter hello all around it
it's more or less spherical right this
is another interesting such picture
so that's how we know that dark matter
exists now what is dark energy Dark
Energy so dark matter what it does is
that it tends to
to it acts like a glue right so it keeps
the Galaxy together it is it it is it
has an attractive gravitational force we
can observe the we can deduce the
existence of Dark Matter also through
the phenomenon of Galactic lensing let
me show you what that looks like
galactic lensing
so something
in Galactic lensing objects appear
distorted as if there's a as if we are
observing that object through a lens so
this is a very very nice example of that
yeah
sometimes you see double images
sometimes you see galaxies that that
look stretched out
and so on so this indicates that there
is a massive object between us and the
Galaxy or the object that we're
observing and that is distorting space
time itself
yeah that is what general relativity
tells us and that's how we know that
there is there is something out there
and that sometimes is an indication of a
black hole or sometimes it tells us
there is a dark matter over there
between us and the object we're
observing so that's how we know Dark
Matter exists dark in in dark matter is
is is massive
and it it has uh an attractive it it the
if the gravitational effect is
attractive dark energy on the other hand
it is something that causes the
expansion of the universe you can think
of dark energy like it's a fifth force
in the universe we know there are four
forces the strong nuclear force the weak
nuclear force the electromagnetic force
and the gravitational force dark energy
is like repulsive gravity
it actually pushes three things apart
we know that the universe is expanding
we know that something is causing the
universe to the accelerate the expansion
of the universe to accelerate
not only is the universe expanding this
expansion is accelerating over time
there is some unknown Force
or energy in the universe that is
causing this to happen and that is what
we call Dark Energy so you can think of
dark energy as as as a fifth Force as a
repulsive form of gravity or whatever
you want to call it and it accounts for
roughly 70 percent of the mass energy
composition of the universe
all right so that's dark matter
roughly 25 percent Dark Energy roughly
70 percent and visible matter of which
we are made which is about five percent
of the mass energy composition of the of
the universe which means we are made up
of special stuff only five percent the
other stuff the common stuff is
invisible we don't know what it is but
it's out there
so that is dark matter and dark energy
thank you
Krishna says if light in the universe is
about 13.8 billion years old how can we
observe the observable universe which
has a radius of more than 40 billion
light years
so uh the best theory that we have of
the origin of the of the universe
is is the so-called Big Bang Theory yes
and we know that the universe is roughly
13.8 billion years old the oldest light
that we observe in the reverse is about
300 million years it's from about 300
million years roughly after the big bang
happened
that is the oldest light in the universe
it's stretched out into the infrared uh
wavelengths and that's what the James
Webb Space Telescope is tasked with
observing so the oldest light is
about let's say around 13.5 billion
years old yes
um
so the most distant objects traveling at
the speed of light would be
13.5
billion years a billion light years away
from us so the observable universe is
like a sphere let me show you what that
looks like
observable
universe what does it look like well
let's take a look at a representation of
that
so let's say that this is a schematic of
the observable universe is this it
okay we're talking about parsecs and all
that
this is a cross section of that
and so on
so what we find is that the radius of
this observable universe is not 13.5
billion light years it's actually about
45 billion light years uh in in radius
so why is it so
so this is a you can explain this quite
simply it's because of the expansion the
accelerating expansion of the universe
because the universe is expanding in an
accelerated rate at an accelerated rate
that's why it has gone so much further
away and the oldest and the furthest
light that we see even though it's just
30.8 30.5 billion years old yet the
radius or the diameter of this of the
observable universe is is so large so
the radius is about 45 46 billion light
years the diameter is about 90 91 92
billion light years because the universe
is expanding and every single day that
passes
there are certain parts of the
observable universe that disappear
forever
because Beyond a certain point the
expansion of space-time becomes
superluminal
it the expansion
becomes faster than the speed of light
light itself and that does not break the
laws of physics
the fastest the speed limit within space
time is the speed of light but space
time itself can expand even faster than
the speed of light
and because of this there are parts of
the observable universe that every
single day every single minute every
single second are going forever beyond
our observational range
right so that's what's happening
eventually in the distant future the
observable universe will be simply the
Milky Way we will be able to observe
nothing beyond that and eventually one
day only the solar system will be left
so that's what's going to happen in the
very distant future because of the
expansion of the universe caused by this
strange thing called this unknown
mysterious substance or Force called
dark energy
okay
okay T1 says can we get our hands on a
bottle of dense dark matter
you know
you can't get your hands on a bottle of
dense dark matter but if you have an
empty bottle in your hand it contains
dark matter
right now
there is dark matter in this room
most likely there is dark matter in this
room
the solar system the Earth passes
through uh
clouds of dark matter like I said there
is a dark matter hello that envelops our
galaxy
or the visible part of the Galaxy is
just a small portion maybe 10 percent
of uh maybe roughly 10 of the mass
energy of the of the entire galaxy
around 90 could be
dark matter which means that we are
enveloped in a massive Hollow massive
cloud of dark matter which means there
is there are dark matter particles right
now in this room where I am and right
now Wherever You Are Dark Matter
particles are passing through your
bodies
as we speak
um and dark matter is most likely some
some particle or some family or class of
particles
that are purely gravitating in nature
they only interact through the
gravitational gravitational force and
not through any of the other three
forces
the gravitational force is many many
many orders of magnitude weaker than the
weak nuclear force solar neutrinos
interact weekly via the weak Force as we
speak every second as we speak trillions
of solar neutrinos pass through our body
right now every second
trillions of these solar neutrinos that
come from the Sun are passing through my
body I don't feel anything
because they interact so weekly
so if that is the weak Force imagine how
weak gravitation is so there are all
these dark matter particles that are
passing through us every single moment
and we don't realize that you have an
empty bottle
most likely there this dark matter
within it but it's passing through it
you cannot confine it in your bottle it
will simply pass through your bottle as
if the bottle doesn't exist
uh so yeah
that's what it is
foreign
says please explain what the Higgs boson
is all right what is the X boson what is
the Higgs field
um so from the point of view
of the standard model the standard model
the standard model of physics says
and this has been experimentally proven
rigorously tested the standard model of
physics tells us that there are 16 known
Elementary particles let me show you
what that looks like
uh
demonstrate that
give me a second please let me share my
screen and show you the standard model
of Elementary
particles
here we are
so we have 16 known particles all right
we have the quarks up down top bottom
strange charm six different kinds of
corks we have six leptons the electron
the MU on the Tau and their
corresponding neutrinos
and you have there used to be four
bosons now there are five bosons
so the glue on the photon the zebos on
the W ozone and the Higgs boson
so these are the various uh
these are the 17 fundamental particles
that we know of and from the perspective
of quantum field Theory Quantum field
Theory tells us that the world that we
inhabit the world that we perceive and
observe is an illusion
what actually the the universe is
actually made of fields interacting
fields and all these Elementary
particles are merely local excitations
in these fields so there is an electron
field that permeates a three-dimensional
electron field that permeates the entire
universe and every single electron in my
body is merely a local excitation in
that in almost infinite electron field
similarly
every proton is made up of quarks the
quarks have their own Fields when they
interact together they form bound states
that appear to be protons and all but
everything is just fields and all these
Elementary particles are local
excitations in these fields now there is
something called a Higgs field so uh in
the 1960s it was proposed that the
Universe we did not understand how where
does mass come from
why are certain Elementary particles
massive why do certain particles have
more mass why are certain particles like
the photon massless why is it so
so I think it was in the 1960s that
Peter Higgs and a couple of other
physicists put for the the the theory
that there is a fifth
Boson which is now called the Higgs
boson and it so if there is a Higgs
boson it will have a Higgs field that
permeates the entire universe and it is
the interaction of particles of
Elementary particles with this Higgs
field that endows them with mass or not
so if some particles interact weekly
with the Higgs field then they have
small masses
if certain particles interact strongly
with the Higgs field they have larger
masses and particles that simply don't
interact with the big with the Higgs
field are massless
so that is what was uh proposed in the
1960s the theory was constructed made
out and in 2012 I believe in the Large
Hadron Collider we finally found
evidence that the Higgs boson does exist
yeah so this particle was finally
discovered after a very long time in
2012 I believe and that is the one major
discovery that we have seen coming out
of the Large Hadron Collider in Geneva
Switzerland
so that's what the Higgs field is that's
what the Higgs bows on is without this
particle the universe would be a
massless place so
so Mass itself is like a force in a way
in a way yeah
so that's why certain particles are more
massive certain particles are less
massive the the most massive particle we
know of is the top Quark once again if
we put that on the screen
the top Quark is the most massive
particle that we know of right you can
see it's 173.1 gev and what that is you
can go you can look it up what are gevs
gev okay so that's the most massive
particle which means that it interacts
very strongly
with the Higgs field there is a very
interesting analogy that people have
given it's not something I have come up
with but it's very interesting to think
of in this way let's say you have
let's say you have a restaurant or let's
say you have a hall okay a big Hall
in which you have lots of people at one
end of this Hall there is a bar where
you can go and get drinks
and the door is at the other end end of
the hall
now when a famous person
comes into the Hall
and they want to get to the bar
it will be hard for them to get there
because everybody converges on them oh
yeah I'll give you I'm I'm a big fan of
yours can I have an autograph can I have
a selfie so it'd be very hard it'll take
a lot of time for the famous person to
cross the hall and reach the bar
so the hall is filled with people and
they all recognize the celebrity and
they all want to go and talk to them but
if a completely unknown person comes
into the Hall
in and wants to go to the bar they would
be able to go without any interaction
with the crowd
so the crowd in this Hall can be thought
of as the Higgs field
and if you are completely unknown you
can pass through the crowd without any
interaction with the field with the
Higgs field so then you are massless but
if you are a celebrity everybody wants
to talk to you so it's very hard to
reach the bar so that is a very massive
particle and a particle that interacts
very strongly with the Higgs field so
that is an interesting analogy that
people have come up with right
so that in brief is about the Higgs
field and the Higgs bows on
devajit says the bright star Sirius is
roughly 8.6 light years away does it
mean that when you see it in the sky
tonight you're actually seeing serious
the way it was 8.6 years ago absolutely
right
light takes 8.6 years to reach here from
that star
so what you are seeing is light that
came from the star
that began its Journey from the Star 8.6
years ago so if you have a telescope
you're looking there you're seeing what
happened 8.6 years ago yeah you're not
something that's you're not saying
something that's happening right now
in in relativity
simultaneously is a tricky concept it
doesn't really happen it's it's not
really a concept that makes sense from
the perspective of Relativity from
special relativity there is the
relativity of simultaneity which you can
study which means that any two events
from a certain perspective can be seen
as happening simultaneously so it
depends on your frame of reference
and where you are and so on but yes from
our perspective from our frame of
reference where we are on our planet
what we see when we observe light from
serious we are seeing something that
happened 8.6 million uh 8.6 years ago
let's say you are observing a Galaxy
that is 10 million years away from here
you look at the telescope and you see
the image
that's you're seeing something that
using light that started its Journey
from there 10 million years before today
so you're seeing what happened there 10
million years ago that's how it is
nikhil says suppose we have a time
machine and we have a pair of quantum
entangled particles we keep one here and
we take one particle back to the past
will the quantum entanglement still work
and if yes can we say that information
can travel across time
well
okay let's first of all understand what
Quantum entanglementing is a very
simplistic analogy
is a pair of gloves
a left-handed glove and a right-handed
glove let's say you are sitting in the
city of Bengaluru
okay and you send one glove
okay let's say you are sitting in in in
Mumbai all right let's say you're
sitting in Mumbai
you
put one glove in a sealed package and
send it to Bengaluru you take the other
glove put it in a sealed package and set
it to Berlin
so your friend in Bangalore receives one
one of the gloves and your friend in
Berlin receives the other glove
now let's say your friend in Berlin
opens the glove and he or she finds a
right-handed glove
then they will immediately know that
your other friend in Bangalore
has a left-handed love
now let's say you send one of the gloves
to the Andromeda galaxy and one of the
other gloves to the two star series
so when your friend on Andromeda
receives the glove and sees what it is
then even though serious is 1.5 million
light years away he or she your alien
friend will immediately know
that your friend on the other star on
Sirius has received the left-handed
glove right
so information
seems to be traveling faster than faster
than the speed of light which is not
quite the case but it's a it's a system
so an entangled system is a Quantum
system whose wave function who which has
a single wave function
that's what it is that's how we could
put it across
so um
when you have information of one part of
the system you immediately know what the
other other part of the system is like
so that is what entanglement is so let's
say like like nikhil is saying we have a
pair of quantum entangled particle let's
say you have two particles one would
spin up one it's pinned down they they
are in a state of entanglement which
means that if you see one particle you
will immediately know what the other
particles a state is right
and he says if we keep one here we take
the other particle back to the past well
that is unphysical
that's where your your uh thought
experiment breaks down
because there is no way of sending
anything back to the past
time machines don't exist
right so the thought experiment is
unphysical your your
adding an element of magic to it
right
so if we were to somehow make it happen
if we were to actually invent a time
machine that could take things back to
the past
if that were possible
then
it could mean that quantum entanglement
could actually happen across time
periods back in time Etc but it's not
information traveling from one place to
another understand that properly what
you really need to understand is that no
information is troubling there is no
superluminal transmission of information
yeah you cannot have communications
through through entanglement it's just
that when you see one particle you
immediately know what the state of the
other particle is and that's all there
is no actual communication or
transmission that is happening so even
if you could send one particle back in
time and keep another one with you
then the person who is let's say 100
years in the past could know what the
other particle is like 100 years in the
future yes but no communication is
happening no transmission is happening
so even if you could do this information
cannot travel through time quantum
entanglement is not about transmission
of information it's not about
communication of information it's just
about a single system
that it is a lot about a system of
particles that has a single uh wave
function who's so if you know one you
know the other the state of the other
one that's all quantum entanglement is
Aditya says there are infinite stars in
the universe but still the night sky is
dark when we are in a rainforest we
cannot even see the sun because of dense
vegetation then why don't we see the
skies filled with stars which are
trillions in number in other words
please explain old bursts Paradox old
birth paradox
uh okay I don't know what old birds
Paradox is but let me address the
question which seems to mean
paradox
the stars are not trillions in number
the approximate number of stars in the
observable universe is about 10 raised
to 24 23 or 24 roughly give or take a
couple of zeros here or there right
so that's an insane number of stars 10
raised to 23 let's say
understand this 10 to the power of 23 1
with 23 zeros is not Infinity it's a
finite number it's a very very large
number hard to imagine hard to
comprehend but it is not Infinity
if there were an infinite number of
stars in the observable universe there
will be a star sitting right here there
will be Stars everywhere right here I
would be inside a stardom
but I'm not inside a star which means
that the number of stars in the universe
is not in finite it is finite it can be
approximated to around 10 minutes or 23
or 24.
so the first assumption that you have
made is not correct
there are not an infinite number of
stars in the universe there is a finite
number of stars and if you look at space
from all the observational evidence that
we have from all the instruments over
all of human history we know
that space is mostly empty
when galaxies Collide they're not really
colliding they're simply merging there
is no actual Collision of stars ever
right
so when in the future our home galaxy
The Milky Way will collide with the
Andromeda galaxy which is traveling
towards us which will happen in a
billion or two billion years or
somewhere in between the actual process
will be a process of the merger of two
galaxies
there will be no actual Collision bang
bang bang of the two galaxies and the
stars that they contain
they'll simply pass to each other and
there'll be a gravitational dance that
will take a couple of billion years or
maybe longer and eventually there will
be a larger Galaxy that will emerge at
the end of the process a larger Galaxy
so that's what it is so uh I don't know
what old Bird's Paradox is but
the the assumption that there is an
infinite number of stars in the universe
is incorrect there is a finite number of
stars and that's why the night sky is
dark if there were an infinite number of
stars the night sky would be as bright
as as the surface of the Sun or even
brighter than that so that is the reason
why the night sky is dark because it's
almost
it's it's mostly empty space the stars
are few and far between not few but the
distances average distance between stars
is of the order of light years right
many light years the closest star to
Earth is about four or so light years
away yeah
Proxima Centauri
and the distance between our galaxy The
Milky Way and the closest the nearest
galaxy Andromeda
is about 1.5 million light years these
are enormous distances so that's why the
night sky is dark
the number of stars is not infinite it's
finite
all right
Ori Jun says don't you think that
theoretical physicists have gone too
much creative and radical in the past
few decades
for instance we are talking about
multiverses parallel universes higher
Dimensions holographic principle Etc
they don't have any experimental grounds
things like the Multiverse are brought
up in discussions as if it's completely
natural and self-evident do you think
physicists need to be more conservative
I would very much like to hear your
views on this
uh I think this might be to the
discovery of qm quantum mechanics and
general relativity
in the 20th century okay PS I'm not sure
what that is but yeah
I have have physicists gone overboard I
think they have to a large extent when
we talk about the string theory
landscape 10 raised to 500 different
universes possible universes Etc what's
the evidence for this
we are going Beyond science when we are
talking about these things science
so there is something about science
that's very clear
any scientific theory
needs to be a testable and B falsifiable
it has to be falsifiable
when we talk about Multiverse when we
talk about parallel universes there is
no way
we are ever going to be able to test it
right we can only observe what exists in
the observable universe the observable
universe is most likely a small subset
of the actual universe that we inhabit
and Beyond the universe if there is
something Beyond there is no way of
knowing what's out there and there's
absolutely no way of testing it or
observing it we can only observe a small
subset of the actual universe so when we
talk about a Multiverse that is
non-testable that is non-falsifiable and
that means that it's not science
yeah mathematically you could come up
with the
scenarios in which there could be
multiple universes yeah sure but it is
not testable it is not falsifiable and
that's why it is something that is not
quite science it is either philosophy or
ideology
yeah and yet you have all of this
becoming mainstreamed
physicists talk about this parallel
universes and things like that yeah
higher higher Dimensions which which we
have never been able to observe well
higher Dimensions is something that's
right here
theoretically so we could try and find
we could try and devise tests of whether
these higher dimensions exist or not uh
many of these higher dimensions are
supposed to be compactified Dimensions
so you can observe them only in the very
small Quantum domain essentially so
maybe we could in the future test that
sort of theory out so that is still
something that's within the realm of
science but when we talk about parallel
universes and the Multiverse that is
just Ah that's not science right
so yes right now we have lost some of
the discipline that that science needs
to have and that's why we are kind of
adrift and we have we have lost we have
in some way lost touch with reality
in the past 30 years there has been no
new progress in physics it's like we
have we have hit a brick wall and we are
going no further yeah there are so many
open problems unsolved problems in
physics
that we have made no progress in in the
past 30 years the last big uh
new breakthrough was was the inflation
in 1980 81 82 thereabouts yeah after
that there's been nothing new any new
progress that has actually been tested
and proven right
so yeah so that's why it looks like
we need a change of approach
right now there's too much group think
in physics
in theoretical physics physics
theoretical physics essentially
especially in the west has been taken
over by the string theory Mafia
they have garnered all the funding for
themselves if you want to do theoretical
physics if you want tenure track in
Academia you need to do what everybody
else is doing which is research in
string theory published
dozens of papers over a short period of
time which establish your credentials
but but which take
physics not one inch forward so that's
what's happening and the system is
broken the system is rotten Academia is
has become very problematic and that's
why we are not seeing any new
or Genuine advances in our understanding
of of the universe
so yes I don't think physicists need to
be conservative I think physicists need
to be wilder in their imagination but
they need to be disciplined
you can be creative imaginative
and wild wild being disciplined what
discipline
all your theories need to be testable
and falsifiable you talk about stuff
that's not falsifiable you need to shut
up don't go there it's pointless it's
pointless I always say don't mix
philosophy and science don't mix
religion and science don't make
spirituality in science these things
don't mix
so that is the discipline scientists
need to
have and that's kind of broken right now
to a certain extent
so yeah that that needs to be brought
back and uh
so yeah that's one of the major problems
we are facing right now in physics
Vishal says what is the barber paradox
hmm the barber paradox
it's it's a
it's a logical Paradox let me
try to remember what it is
it says there's a claim you make a claim
that if you are a barber
you shave the people
who are not Barbers and who don't shave
themselves okay
so this is a claim that is made okay
a barber is a person
who shaves those people who are not
Barbers and who don't shave themselves
two components people who are not
barbers
and people who don't shave themselves
the the combination of these two
criteria
so if you are a barber you shaving
people who are not Babas first of all
and who also don't shave themselves
so that's what a barber does but that
means that the barber doesn't shave
himself because he's a barber
so I am a bar but let's say I'm I am the
barber we're talking about let's say so
I am a barber I shave people who are not
Babas and people who don't shave
themselves
so that means that I don't shave myself
I only shave others because I'm a barber
but that means that I've fulfilled one
of these two criteria
right we we are already making the
presupposition that I am a barber
so that is what's called a logical
paradox
and the solution is very simple such a
barber doesn't exist
right so that is the barber paradox
which seems to be an unresolvable
Paradox but this solution is simple that
the Assumption itself is incorrect such
a barber simply cannot exist yeah
so that is what the barber paradox is
do scientists need to recall and
remember every formula or derivation
they learned while doing research or
study I always wanted can a scientist
crack the idg in two minutes or do they
also need to scratch their brains
thinking and solving tough problems
because whenever I try to remember all
the formula and derivations of class 11
for JE
sometimes I become mad but I am more or
less very good in math I don't have such
infinite recalling ability of all
formula and derivations
see scientists don't need to memorize
all the equations and all the formulas
you ask me to write down the the the the
the
navier Stokes equation I I probably will
make some mistake in that right
uh but if if you ask a fluid dynamics
researcher to write down the navius
talks equation that person will do it
immediately he or she could do it in the
sleep
yeah
you ask me to write down other equations
it's holding the equation the Maxwell's
equations I could do it in my sleep so
it depends there are certain things that
you use as tools on a daily basis
those will be burned deep into your
memory but physics is so vast it has so
many subfields you ask me about
condensed metaphysics I will remember
next to nothing right now you asked me
about fluid dynamics yeah so and so
that's how it is
the thing is this when you use certain
tools certain equations certain
techniques certain mathematical things
are tools that you use on a daily basis
that you don't need to memorize it will
be there into it will be burned into
your brain because of repeated use again
and again and again
so when you're an active scientist when
you're an active physicist you need to
remember you will remember
stuff that you use on a daily basis
but other stuff you you can afford to
forget
right
uh so scientists don't need to recall
and remember every formula every
definition every equation they learned
while studying while as a students
but the thing is this that when you want
to become a scientist you have to go
through the Jee if you want to go into
engineering into the iits uh there is
the physics GRE for people who want to
go to go to International institutions
and all in these exams you have to
memorize large vast quantities of facts
of equations of formula uh formula and
so on and you would memorize all kinds
of different techniques of solving
problems on the spot within within a
certain time period there's a time
pressure and you memorize things
um so what you're actually learning is
how to pass exams even the GRE to some
extent is is not really an indicator of
how good of a physicist you're going to
be in the long run
but it does
indicate so if you do well in the
iit-jee or in the physics GRE or
whatever other GRE it indicates that you
are a person who is capable of a
sustained period of focused dedicated
hard work which is a sign of
conscientiousness which is one of the
qualities that a good scientist must
have right so that's how it is the
Indian academic system is broken you
have to memorize stuff and pass exams
and you don't really learn anything
but in the case of this high stakes
exams like the iit-jee the physics GRE
and other Gres Etc there is an element
of some of that actually matters so
that's how it is
that's just how it is that's the way the
system is built it actually proves that
you are capable and you are willing of
of being disciplined you're capable of
being disciplined you're capable of
putting in a sustained period of really
intense and hard work of memorizing all
these things and solving lots of
problems which is a good indicator of
law long-term success in life
so that's how it is it is something you
have to do so you got to do it
manmad tiwari says my sister is in class
seventh her physics teacher recently in
a unit test deducted three marks for
writing units in the form of this with
the with the carrot cm squared instead
of square cm three marks for this it
makes me wonder that whether we are able
to reform the system education system
how will we reform the teacher's
mentality
um
you're right
I have come across such teachers
I remember when I was in what standard
seventh or something
I had to draw something on europass
exams you know don't draw diagrams it
was a diagram of some kind of apparatus
in physics that had to do something with
sunlight and in the textbook it was it
was drawn in a certain fashion I did not
memorize the thing I understood it
conceptually and I draw it I drew it in
a different configuration in a different
orientation but which made perfect
physical sense and I lost five marks
because my teacher said no that's not
how it is in the textbook
most teachers
well you know I I don't want to be rude
I would say that most teachers are
idiots which is true
most of them are well meaning
this is the way they studied stuff that
is what makes sense to them and that's
why they think that if you don't
replicate things exactly the way they're
in textbooks then you're doing something
wrong
when you don't replicate what's in the
textbook but you give the right answer
it means that you are you are actually
capable of thinking
but this education system emphasizes
obedience and memorization not actual
critical thinking and that's the main
problem in the education system today so
if we are to reform the education system
we will have to reform the teachers as
well and Beyond a certain age after a
certain age let's say 35 40 people
simply are not most people are not
capable of changing so yeah we will have
to bring in new teachers
the best teachers are will be the ones
who are in the 20s who are capable of
changing what capable of learning we
need to when the reforms are done
eventually we will have to
to retire all most of the existing
teachers there's no way around it unless
they are willing to change
and bring in fresh minds and fresh blood
so yes that is something that will have
to be done with the current crop of
teachers we will not see changes their
minds are still the same the mentality
and attitudes are still the same and
that's going to be problematic so when
the reforms are done we will need
younger people to come in people who are
receptive to change
so that's what needs to happen
eventually
sort of says as a scientist yourself do
you view the Indian Academy how do you
view the Indian Academia
in its present state
I've witnessed an obsession obsession
with each index course amongst our
academicians there's a stiff obsession
with grades number of papers polished
Publications in repeated journals Etc on
the other hand our institutions research
outputs are still meager and namesake
have the elite Indian institutions only
become High salary Workforce providers
or is there still a hope for qualitative
research coming out so I've gone to
detail about these things in episode
3031 thereabouts yeah a long time ago I
mean about a year or so ago in which
I've spoken about this in detail but let
me address your question
how do I see in an Academia Indian
Academia is the epitome of mediocrity
that's what it is
forget about what you're saying
in most colleges and universities there
is no emphasis on Research at all
nowadays I think the ugc this obsolete
thing
institution organization has mandated
that there needs to be a certain number
of research output so you have this
third rate research journals that have
cropped up like mushrooms everywhere in
which you can essentially get some
research paper published for a fee
so that's the new scam that's going on
in an Indian Academia all these
so-called research journals that have
cropped up yeah
uh it's it's a it's a farce the Indian
academic system is a farce and even in
the top level institutions the you know
the top 10 percent or whatever they do
publish it's publish or perish but
what's the quality what's the output are
they doing any real research no they're
not
I would say about two percent or three
percent of the academicians in India
would be like world class 97 98 will be
it would be mediocre people who have no
interest in research who have no
interest in progress
they're just in it for the salary
and for the job security that's how it
is
um
yeah so so it's it's it's a morass of
mediocrity I I know it very well I've
spent most of my life in the academic
system I know it intimately I've gone
through the grind it's terrible it needs
to be changed wholesale and when the
changes happen when the reforms happen
the current lot of academicians needs to
be uh retired
with whatever
pension they would acquire otherwise and
let them go and we need fresh blood into
the system when whenever the government
decides to reform the system a so yeah
that that's what it is
an amazing Indian citizen says that you
have said that in order to get become
good at physics mathematics chemistry
Etc we need to solve lots of problems
yes I have said that but what to do when
you're unable to solve a problem you
directly jump to the solution or do you
try solving it again
think about it this way
let's say you're a sports person yeah
let's say let's say you're playing
cricket cricket
and you need to take 10 wickets to win
the match let's say you're a bowler fast
bowler and you're on a team with five
other guys or girls whatever yeah you
need to take 10 wickets to win the match
and consistently you're able to only get
five or six wickets and you keep losing
what do you do
so you know how to bowl
but you don't quite at the skills of how
to get certain people out so you need to
acquire those skills you need to look at
what you're doing wrong
whether you're doing something wrong
mentally you whether you're doing
something wrong biomechanically whether
you're the wrong strategy
so when you are unable to solve a
problem you have to step back and
analyze where you are going wrong
what skill do you lack
problem solving is a bunch of skills
it's a it's a bunch of it's a toolkit
that you have mathematical toolkit in
physics to solve problems right
so maybe your deficient in one of the
mathematical uh aspects maybe you're not
good at calculus maybe you're not good
at differential equations maybe there
are certain classes of differential
equations you can solve maybe you're bad
at a linear algebra maybe you don't you
know you don't quite know how to use
matrices whatever right
figure out where you're going wrong and
then work on that address that
deficiency that's simply how it works
you can jump to the solution but that
will teach you nothing the best way of
learning something is failing repeatedly
then stepping back and looking at why am
I failing
and then once you identify the reason
why you're not able to solve the problem
you you identify that and then you work
on that
skill and then you'll be able to solve
it and of course it helps to eventually
go and look at the solution and see how
did they go about solving the problem
and so on right so it's a you have to be
patient but you have to be proactive you
to move fast you have to identify your
deficiencies and weaknesses and work on
them right so that sort of conscious
practice if you do you'll be able to
progress
Abhijit Verma says do you like the TV
series The Big Bang Theory there used to
be another comedy series called the
Third Rock From the Sun how did you find
the humor in that among the dramas how
do you rate Star Trek and which other
series do you recommend for scientists
with thinking and Funny Bone
um I used to like Star Trek the initial
original one with William Shatner as
Captain Kirk that was nice I used to
like that I saw it when I was I don't
know teenager or something
uh I liked that the first the first run
with with those characters
uh The Big Bang Theory was funny uh
people actually think physicists are
like that like like the guy Sheldon
Cooper right I think the first season
was funny the first couple of seasons
were quite funny then it got
a kind of stale which was unfortunate uh
Third Rock From the Sun if I remember
remember watching a few episodes when I
was when I was a kid I think
that was quite funny yeah
yeah so
uh
so I I rate the original Star Trek
series quite highly
there was something called Star Trek the
Next Generation from the 90s I believe
that was also quite good
uh and that took a couple of seasons to
get into the stride but it was quite
good afterwards
uh yeah so
and what series do I recommend for
scientists with the funny with the
thinking and funny bone
um
um I I'm not able to think of any
interesting uh science fiction or such
uh Series right now I'll I quite like
the movie Interstellar it it was
reasonably well grounded in physics and
the story was also quite good
and among TV series I can't think of any
science fiction series right now but but
how about I I think about it and I get
back to you the next time yeah
right
okay so that brings us to the end of
today's questions let's take a look if
you have some questions ask me now on
the live chat and maybe I'll take a few
questions right now
so go ahead and ask me questions Black
Mirror Black Mirror is an interesting
one I had seen maybe one or two episodes
of that
that was interesting yes I don't have I
don't quite have the time to watch TV
series and all that but yeah
Black Mirror was interesting I'd seen a
couple of episodes of that
uh
is Homeopathy a pseudoscience what are
its Origins
I believe Homeopathy originates in 18th
or 19th century Germany I think
and it is very definitely pseudoscience
um you know there is this term
called a homeopathic dose a homeopathic
dose of anything is an ineffective dose
a very very incredibly dilute dose yeah
so Homeopathy is I don't remember
exactly what the tenets and the
principles of Homeopathy are but what I
do know is that the dose ages of
whatever active substances are used are
so incredibly low
that they are they are never going to
work and there is something called there
is this concept I believe of water
retaining memory of stuff
of water retaining memory of what
substance you put in it and then the
water itself is going to work for you or
something like that and these Concepts
or these ideas have no
bases in actual science right
so overall what I can say is that
Homeopathy is indeed pseudoscience in
India most people Club Homeopathy with
ayurveda which is incorrect
ayurveda
is actually something that has
active ingredients herbal ingredients
which which have not been studied well
but whatever is studied seems to work
for instance brahmi it is now used in in
a nootropic combinations brahmi is is a
is a plant
it's a herb that enhances cognitive
function and that seems to be proven
right and there are lots of other herbs
Arjuna for instance and so on yeah in in
ayurveda
that scientists thus far have kind of
refused to study in detail
but they have been tested over thousands
of years so ayurveda is not
pseudoscience but Homeopathy certainly
is right
foreign
do we have anything else
uh
if the universe is expanding is the can
there be a chance of forming a new
Galaxy every day every week every month
every year every second
um
uh Galaxy formation I think it's
something that takes
a much longer time than the process of
forming Stars
uh
when did the first galaxies form form uh
the James Webb Telescope which is
currently in operation
recently uh
gave us an image of the oldest known
Galaxy which dates back to about about
roughly 250 million years after the big
bang
so it's clear that galaxies formed very
quickly after the big after the initial
Big Bang expansion
230 to 50 million years after the big
bang so galaxies seem to have formed in
the earlier
stages of phases of the universe when
the universe was much smaller and when
stars were were they they were closed
close together and uh
yeah so I don't know if you have if we
see any galaxies actively forming right
now we do see stars actively forming
there are certain regions Stellar
nurseries in various regions of space
within our own Galaxy in other places as
well where stars stars you can see them
actively forming you can see
protostellar discs you can see planets
forming and all but I as far as I know
we don't
see any galaxies forming from clusters
of stars and all that yeah so
it looks like the chance of forming new
galaxies is something that has not been
calculated the rate of formation of
galaxies we don't see any active
actively forming Galaxy right now it's
an interesting question that you've
asked and I don't quite have the answer
to it as far as I know we don't have any
number
for how many for the rate of the
formation of galaxies we know at what
rate stars form but not galaxies and as
far as I know there is no actively
forming Galaxy that we are aware of
right now interesting question
okay let's take some other questions
if we can
are multilingual people more intelligent
and how many languages can I speak
uh It is believed that multilingual
people are they they perform better on
intelligence tests and cognitive tests
and the Brain develops differently yeah
so if you are multilingual if you make
the effort of learning more than one or
two languages it kind of
helps you cognitively and maybe it
contributes to a hierarchy IQ or for a
higher intelligence overall yeah that's
possible how many languages can I speak
four at least and there are certain
languages that I can speak you know I
can I can throw out a few phrases
phrases of some certain some languages
here and there it's all based on
language families if you so if you know
one language you can kind of understand
other languages that are closely related
to that if you can speak Hindi well most
languages in northern and western India
will make sense to you if you can speak
any of the Western European languages
most of the languages in that region
could be somewhat intelligible to you
and so on so I can speak four languages
properly and uh other languages here and
there I can throw out a few
words or phrases yeah
all right
um
Newton or Einstein both both were both
made the significant contributions in
their own right
yeah
okay please don't ask me questions about
history today my dear friends today is
about science
um
let us see
do we have anything else
okay Louis says if you can see the past
of stars when we observe observe the
night sky firstly can we theoretically
at least see our own remote past of the
Sun and of our planet
well it depends on where they are so if
we are sitting here and we are observing
the Andromeda galaxy we are seeing light
that began its Journey from there 1.5
million years before today so we are
observing the past of the Andromeda
galaxy if we are looking at the sun
we are seeing light that emerged from
the Sun eight minutes ago the distance
between the Earth and the Sun is eight
light minutes it takes light eight
minutes to travel from the Sun to the
Earth so we are seeing the past of the
sun itself so the question is can we
theoretically see our own remote past
theoretically if you were to teleport
yourself
to the Andromeda Galaxy
and you were to observe the Earth from
there you would be observing something
that happened 1.1.5 mil
ion years in the earth's past
so
um
so maybe you could see the ancestors of
humanity if you could somehow teleport
yourself there and we don't have any
means of doing that but theoretically if
you were there then yes so theoretically
if I could
make a spaceship or or a wormhole that
would instantaneously take me there to
some place in the Andromeda galaxy and
then if I would observe the earth I
would be seeing what happened on the
earth 1.5 million years before today the
early humans you know that had just
split off from our chimpanzee cousins
and so on so theoretically it is
possible but practically unfortunately
we don't have the technology or the
means of making that happen so it
depends on where you are located
so in that in that manner we could
possibly see our remote past of our
planet and our solar system
okay my friends that's the last question
for today we are done for today two
hours crossed thank you very much always
great fun talking to you all and I will
see you in tomorrow's live stream which
will be about other topics all right
thank you very much take care
stay healthy and I will see you in the
next episode bye